<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two letters concerning the Holy Trinity reconciling together in some measure the semi-Arian and the Trinitarian systems, concerning Christ's divinity, and inquiring, whether the term persons, speaking of God, shou'd be impos'd in acts of church-communion : to be offered to the consideration of the learned, in order to their giving their opinion and reasons concerning the things herein mentioned.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64013</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38384</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17356100</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17356100</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106417</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64013)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106417)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1106:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two letters concerning the Holy Trinity reconciling together in some measure the semi-Arian and the Trinitarian systems, concerning Christ's divinity, and inquiring, whether the term persons, speaking of God, shou'd be impos'd in acts of church-communion : to be offered to the consideration of the learned, in order to their giving their opinion and reasons concerning the things herein mentioned.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>168-?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 16.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Unitarianism --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Trinity.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106417:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106417:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TWO LETTERS, Concerning the HOLY TRINITY; Reconciling together in ſome meaſure the <hi>Semi-Arian</hi> and the <hi>Trinitarian</hi> Syſtems, concerning Chriſt's Divinity; and Inquiring, Whether the Term <hi>Perſons,</hi> ſpeaking of God, ſhou'd be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd in Acts of Church-Communion?</head>
            <head type="sub">To be offered to the Conſideration of the Learned, in order to their giving their Opinion and Reaſons concerning the things herein mentioned.</head>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>The Firſt LETTER; being a Preparatory of the Matter, more fully treated of in the Second.</head>
               <p>***</p>
               <p>I Conſume my Spirits daily, in ſtudying more and more the Doctrine of the Trinity, and cannot ceaſe that Study, for fear I ſhould be wanting to my Duty on the one Hand or the other. But after all, I can find no Reſt, but in the ſeeming Generality of the Expreſſions of Scripture. I believe there may be more implied in thoſe Expreſſions, or they may import otherwiſe, then all Men are aware of. But then, the Scripture being ſo Myſterious and Obſcure about this Point, doth it not ſeem to be to the intent, to try the beſt Induſtry and Search of every one in particular, and our Moderation in ſo intricate and difficult a Matter, and ſo to lead and oblige
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106417:2"/>us to bear with one another in different Sentiments herein, uniting in the Scripture-Generality, no Man being to judge for another? The Ancients, ſo far as I can perceive, ſeem very much Divided and Uncertain in their Judgment about this Obſcure Subject. By the Expreſſions of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Doctors that began to Platonize among Chriſtians, it ſeems that they inclined moſt to <hi>Semi-Arianiſm,</hi> as I alſo in ſome meaſure do, mollifying the <hi>Arian</hi> Syſtem, as I think is the true Import of it, rationally underſtood.</p>
               <p>I ſeek only Counſel and Inſtruction, and deſire to be truly Humble and Moderate as I ought to be, and pray God I may actually diſcharge my whole Duty. I believe, that the Godhead is as intimately United with Chriſt as poſſible, and that not only the Divine Power continually aſſiſts him, ſo that he diſpoſes of it as a Man diſpoſes of his Arms or Hands, (which is merely by Deſiring or Willing,) but alſo that the Divine Wiſdom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly illuminates and conducts his Soul, as our Soul doth our Body, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that he is thereby enabled to repreſent God at the Head of the Univerſe. And I do not ſee what more than this can be underſtood by the Union of the Divine with Chriſt's Human Nature. Wherefore, by this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, the <hi>Semi-Arian</hi> and <hi>Trinitarian</hi> Syſtems ſeem herein to be nearly reconciled together.</p>
               <p>By the Holy Ghoſt, or Holy Spirit, I underſtand the Divine and Sanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Inſpiration, and the Miraculous (or Wonder-working) Divine Power, communicated in ſome meaſure to ſome Men, according to the good Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God, together with the concurring Miniſtry of ſome Angel, as ſeems to be inferr'd from ſeveral Places of Scripture, particularly, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1, 35. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5, 21. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1, 7, compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 2, 3, 4. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1, 14, compared with <hi>John,</hi> 16, 13. <hi>Acts</hi> 8, 26, 29, 39.</p>
               <p>I believe then, that there is in God, the Divine Mind, the Divine Wiſdom, and the Divine Power. Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> aſſerted, that it was ſufficient to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge theſe Divine <hi>Properties,</hi> and that it was not neceſſary to inſiſt on the term <hi>Perſons.</hi> (<hi>Inſtit. Cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Sect.</hi> 25. <hi>p.</hi> 179. <hi>Genev.</hi> 1550.) St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> owns it to be very improper. (<hi>De Trin.</hi> L. 5, C. 9.) St. <hi>Jerom</hi> declared, he cou'd not uſe it. <hi>(Epiſt ad Papam Damas.)</hi> I am of the ſame Opinion. I have prepared a Second Letter, humbly to repreſent my Reaſons for it. If I mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake in my Sentiment, I hope I am but of thoſe Weak in the Faith, who may be received, and whom God will receive. I conclude, moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching you to compaſſionate me, and to grant me your Prayers, being, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106417:2"/>
               <head>The Second Letter.</head>
               <p>***</p>
               <p>THIS Controverſy ſeems exceeding intricate and difficult, after the matureſt and carefulleſt Conſideration of it. But then, ſeeing the Scripture expreſſes it ſelf ſo obſcurely and in ſo general terms concerning that Subject, it ſeems that, as was intimated in the former Letter, it is to the intent to try our Moderation, as well as every ones beſt Induſtry in particular, and that we ſhould not be too Deciſive and Impoſing, and ſhould not condemn, but ſhould bear with one another herein, and ſhould unite and agree in the ſeeming Generality of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Scripture, conſidering that ſincere Perſons may miſtake about ſo obſcure a Point, and conſidering that a hearty Love of God and of Chriſt cannot but be acceptable to them, that the main things are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured when the Expreſſions of Scripture are adhered to in this Matter, that it will in all probability ſuffice to have a fuller Knowledge of it after this Life, that in the mean time we are not to judge for one another, and that after all there is not probably ſo much Difference as has been ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined between the contending Parties. There would have been no Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union, if Chriſtians had ſeriouſly made thoſe reflections, and had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented themſelves with this ſcriptural and general Profeſſion, that the Word is God, that the Holy Spirit or Inſpiration and Power of God is God, that theſe three, the Father, the Word, and the Spirit are one, and that there is but one God. There may undoubtedly, as I ſaid, be more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in theſe Expreſſions, or they may import otherwiſe, than ſome Men, or all Men, are aware of. Howbeit, the Scripture being thus general, ſeems to require indiſpenſibly no more than this general Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And therefore Proteſtants, particularly owning that they are not to judge for one another, can juſtly require no more for Terms of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And then all Chriſtians, that are ſincere, cannot but be ſafe; for, ſincerely believing the Scripture, as Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> ſomewhere obſerves, they believe implicitely even thoſe very Truths and Senſes which perhaps they are ſomewhat ſhort in.</p>
               <p>For my part, God is Witneſs I conſider this Subject to the beſt of my Power, and act and proceed ſincerely herein, howſoever I may ſometimes differ from former Sentiments, and be ſometimes perplexed in my Thoughts. But after the fulleſt conſideration, it ſeems to me, it is not impoſſible that the <hi>Arian</hi> or <hi>Socinian</hi> Syſtems be true, and yet not impoſſible but that that Syſtem alſo be true, which by the Word and Holy Spirit underſtands God himſelf, or the Acts and Properties of the Father, (tho' indeed it ſeems very improper to ſay, God the Wiſdom, and God the Power.)</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:106417:3"/>
               <p>Inconteſtably there is in God, as was ſaid, a Divine Mind, a Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and a Divine Will or Power. Nevertheleſs, even tho' by <hi>the Word</hi> in the beginning of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel ſhould be underſtood the Divine Reaſon or Wiſdom, produced forth or ſhewn in the Old and New Creation, (there ſaid therefore, by a Figure, to be Incarnate, that is, moſt intimately to dwell with and aſſiſt the Human Spirit of that Man who is the chiefeſt of God's Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers;) it hinders not, but that at the ſame time by <hi>the Word</hi> may be meant the Soul of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> which (for the reaſons uſually alledged for that part of the <hi>Arian</hi> Sentiment) it is credible was the firſt Creature, and which was God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as this Spirit not only was the Firſt-born and Heir of all the Creation, and was deſigned the Chief of all Creatures, but alſo was ſo filled with the Divine Wiſdom, and aſſiſted with the Divine Power, that the Godhead was from the beginning as intimately united with this Holy Soul as poſſible, which it was not with any other, in which Senſe, among others, (as upon the account of his being the Creature the moſt like to God, as alſo by reaſon of his ſingular partaking of the Divine Soveraignty and Authority,) this <hi>Word,</hi> or Word bearer, may be called God's only Son. And, as I take it, there can be meant no more by the Hypoſtatick Union.</p>
               <p>Now, ſeeing the <hi>Arians</hi> hold that Chriſt was <hi>Inſtrumental in Creating or Ordering of the World,</hi> and the <hi>Socinians</hi> ſay he is <hi>Deus factus,</hi> inſomuch that, as both Parties own, he can act in all things as God, govern the World, raiſe the Dead, judge all Men, and do whatſoever the Father can do; they muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be underſtood to ſuppoſe ſuch a Communication as I have ſpecified of the Divine Nature to the Spirit of Chriſt, whereby the Fullneſs of the Godhead ſo dwells in and conducts and aſſiſts him, and acts by him, that what God doth is reckoned to be done by Chriſt, being done by the Divine Vertue, both, dwelling in him, and diſpoſed of by him according to his Deſire. What Chriſt doth in the diſcharge of his Office may be imputed to God aſſiſting him and dwelling in him; In like manner, what is moſt properly the Work of God may be aſcribed to Chriſt, procuring it to be done, by his Application to the Godhead dwelling in him.</p>
               <p>Conſidering then as exactly as I can what can be meant by the Hypoſtatical Union of the Divine with Chriſt's Human Nature, tho' the term, Hypoſtatick Union, be not ſcriptural, nor ſtrictly proper, it ſeems not impoſſible in a ſufficient meaſure to come to a right underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in that Matter; ſeeing all Parties acknowledge, and the Scripture teaches, the Fulneſs of the Godhead dwells in the Man Chriſt Jeſus, ſo that he is aſſiſted and conducted thereby, (as the Human Body is by the Human Soul,) and by that means Chriſt is in God and God in Chriſt, who ſees Chriſt ſees God, all that is God's is Chriſt's, and he can do all that God doth, and God is in him to receive our Homages thro his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation, and, when in that manner Chriſt is worſhipped, God, who is thus intimately united to him, is worſhipped, Chriſt inconteſtably being to be adored or reverenced, according to his moſt high Station and Dignity, to the Glory of the Father, being enabled to be a fit Object of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106417:3"/>our Service, or of our Submiſſion as well as Veneration, by the Divine Wiſdom and Power inhabiting in him, and by the Supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Honour which it has pleas'd God to communicate to him, and inveſt him with, appointing him to repreſent God, and making him moſt intimately partaker of the Divine Nature, ſo that in adoring Chriſt there is no Idolatry, as in the Invocation of Saints, who have received from God neither that Dignity nor Power that Chriſt has, God having put his Name moſt eminently in him. Yet the Nature of the Thing, as well as the Practice of Scripture, ſhews it is neceſſary we then ſhould direct our Prayers and Worſhip ultimately to God in Chriſt, when proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Religious Prayers and Divine Worſhip.</p>
               <p>Thus Chriſt is the Man Jeſus, anointed with the Spirit or Inſpiration and Power of God, aſſiſted and conducted by the Divine Wiſdom, and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately united to the God-head, and therefore in that ſence he is truly ſaid to be God, which, as far as I can underſtand, as I ſaid, is all that can be meant by the Hypoſtatick Union, and, ſo, at the bottom, there need be no Difference about that Point, but all Parties in this manner may agree about it, tho' properly the Title, Son, or the Name, Jeſus Chriſt, denotes the Man, in whom the Godhead dwells and with whom the Godhead is as much united as poſſible, (as is obſerved by <hi>Grotius,</hi> in his <hi>Annotations,</hi> on <hi>Matth.</hi> 1, 16, and <hi>Col.</hi> 1, 16,) tho the Man properly be not the Godhead it ſelf, no more than the Body is the Soul, and tho this Man be properly God, or a God, in an inferiour ſenſe, in as much as, as he repreſents God, ſo he is the Soveraign of the Univerſe under God; (<hi>John</hi> 10, 35;) ſo that properly the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is the only true God, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8, 6. <hi>John,</hi> 17, 3. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4, 6,) and it is He, who by his Divine Wiſdom is ſaid to dwell in our Saviour, (<hi>John,</hi> 14, 10.) which In-dwelling therefore of the Godhead in the Man Jeſus Chriſt I take to be what may be meant by the term, the Hypoſtatick Union.</p>
               <p>But after all the conſideration I am capable of, I cannot find that the term, that there are three Perſons in God, can be in any meaſure juſtifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For there is no reaſon, why the Divine Wiſdom and Power ſhould be looked upon as diſtinct Perſons from the Father, (the Father, as we have ſeen, being ſaid to dwell thereby in Chriſt,) any more than there is, that a Man's Reaſon and Will, or that his right Hand and left Hand, ſhould be ſaid to be diſtinct Perſons from him.</p>
               <p>A Perſon is ſomething intelligent, ſubſiſting of it ſelf. But whatſoever is in God, whether Wiſdom or Power, cannot ſubſiſt from or without the Divine Mind. All things in God avowedly are inſeparable from one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and therefore it muſt be owned no one of them diſtinctly can ſubſiſt of it ſelf, it being abſolutely neceſſary for all of them to ſubſiſt together, and in particular the Divine Power and Wiſdom neceſſarily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the Divine Mind. They are, as in an Human Spirit, Properties and Acts or Powers of the Mind, and not Perſons, (tho' Perſonal Acts may be aſcribed to them, by a Figure common in all Languages, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106417:4"/>in the Stile of Scripture, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.1. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30, 16. <hi>John,</hi> 3, 8. <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.1. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119, 24)</p>
               <p>A Single Perſonal Pronoun is always uſed in Scripture, in ſpeaking of God. And therefore God is to be held one Perſon, and not three Perſons.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, that what may be known of God, is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernible by the Light of Nature, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 1, 19.) But certainly the Light of Nature teaches not, that God is three Perſons, but one, who is All-wiſe and Powerfull.</p>
               <p>A Divine Perſon muſt compriſe all Divine Perfections. For it muſt be All-Perfect; otherwiſe it were not God, ſo as to include, as it is ſaid each Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doth, the whole Divine Nature and Eſſence: For God is All-Perfect. Now one ſuch Perſon muſt be All-Sufficient. Conſequently others cannot be Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. There cannot, therefore, be any other, or any more than one, Perſon in God. For all that is in God is Neceſſary.</p>
               <p>Moreover, to ſuppoſe three All-Sufficient or All-Perfect Perſons, implies three Gods; for every All-Perfect Perſon, ſubſiſting of its ſelf, muſt have in it ſelf whatſoever is neceſſary to the conſtituting of a true, intire and diſtinct God: The aſſerting therefore three diſtinct Divine Perſons, is to aſſert ſo many Gods. And, ſo, it is very important, for the Honour of Chriſtianity and all the Concerns of Religion, to be freed from that Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtick term, which ſets up Polytheiſm, diſguiſes the moſt excellent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, deſtroys the Purity and Simplicity of the Goſpel, and appears con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory and impoſſible.</p>
               <p>If the Son were a Divine Perſon as the Father, this <hi>Contradiction</hi> would follow, that the Divine <hi>Eſſence</hi> were both <hi>Begotten,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbegotten;</hi> for each Perſon is ſaid to be <hi>the ſame Eſſence together with a peculiar Relation.</hi> A Relation alone is not ſaid to be a Perſon, but a Relation with the Eſſence. Therefore <hi>the Eſſence</hi> with a peculiar Relation muſt be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbegotten,</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> Eſſence with another Relation muſt be <hi>Begotten.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Scripture ſays, (<hi>Mark</hi> 13, 32,) the Son knew not ſomething that God knew, (the Fulneſs of the Godhead imparting its influences to him at one time more than at another, as the Soul doth to the Body, inſomuch that Chriſt grew in Knowledge, and not communicating it's Nature to the Human Spirit in which it dwells, ſo as to make it ceaſe to be a Creature or a Finite Being.) Now, not only there are not two Sons in Chriſt, but it is not rational, nor the Stile of any Language, to deny ſimply, or in general terms, of a Being, what is true of any Part of him. Therefore, denying that the Son knew what God knew, it appears that by the Son the Scripture doth not underſtand the Divine Nature, but the Human; (tho', by a Figure, poſſibly, by the Son we may mean that Influence of the Divine Wiſdom and Power, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to, and dwells in, the Son, the Man Chriſt.) This Argument is illuſtrated, in the 1ſt. Book of <hi>Crell</hi>'s Treatiſe, <hi>Touching one God, the Father,</hi> Sect. 2, Chap. 9.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, that the Father only knew of that Day, (<hi>Matth.</hi> 24, 36.) There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Father only is the God, who thus dwells by his Wiſdom in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106417:4"/>Soul of Jeſus, ſo as to be intimately united therewith, as was ſaid. This is confirm'd by <hi>Crell</hi>'s obſervations (in the firſt Chapter of his aforeſaid Book) on <hi>John,</hi> 17, 3. And in many other Places the Scripture is expreſs, that the Father is the only Perſon who is God, in the true or proper Senſe of that word, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8, 6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4, 6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, and it ſeems thus only, the Divine Unity is preſerved and eſtabliſh'd. And if ſo, the Scholaſtick Terms ſhould not be impoſed. There is a ſmall Octavo on that Subject, intituled, <hi>Apologia pro Irenico Magno,</hi> which I wiſh were conſidered, and anſwered if anſwerable; the ſaid Octavo and its Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments being propoſed as intended, to know the Reaſons of others on this Subject.</p>
               <p>By the Holy Spirit, it ſeems the Scripture underſtands the Divine Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Miraculous Power, (as was intimated in the Firſt Letter,) common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joined with or annexed to and communicated by the Elect Angels, (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5, 21,) particularly the Seven Archangels, (<hi>Revel.</hi> 1, 4,) the Firſt whereof undoubtedly is the Chief of the Angels, not perſonally united with the Divine Power, or God, (for he doth not repreſent God at the Head of the Univerſe,) but, as an inferiour Officer, acting in concurrence with the Divine Power. This, as was ſhewn, ſeems to be deducible from ſeveral Texts of Scripture: And ſo the Holy Spirit is both the Divine Power, and the Angels whom God employs. God is pleaſed to work with them, and to have them work with him. Therefore God employing them in his Works, and particularly in the Service of the Church, they are ſubject to it's Head, the Governour of the World, for whom all the Parts of the Univerſe, and all Things whether in Heaven or Earth, were created to the Glory of God, being diſpoſed of by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the beſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which is moſt agreeable to God.</p>
               <p>God ſpeaks by his Word, (or Word-bearer, the Firſt-born, who is as it were the Mouth of God, or his Speaker,) and the Angels obey; and the Divine Power co-operates, and concurs with them. God in the beginning ſhewed the Son what was to be done. And the Son ſhewed it to the Chief of the Angels, when they were created and, with the concurrence of the Word, appointed to their ſeveral Stations. God did work before the Son. And the Son did work like him, being enabled by the Father, taught by the Divine Wiſdom, and ſeconded by the Angels, when created, but aſſiſted by infinite Power. But the Work is aſcribed to the Soveraign and the Firſt Actor under him, as the taking of a Town is aſcribed to the General, and to the Prince by whoſe Authority he acts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This Syſtem ſeems to account for thoſe Places of Scripture, which import, that Chriſt created or diſpoſed all things together with God, that the Son can do nothing of himſelf, but that what he ſees the Father do, he doth the like, (the Son ſeeing, thereby, what he is to deſire of the Divine Power, as <hi>Grotius</hi> notes, on <hi>John</hi> 5, 19, 20, 21.) and that Chriſt is the Word of God, and that he is a God, that the Angels are Miniſtring Spirits, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:106417:5"/>
               <p>Till his Incarnation, <hi>the Word,</hi> or aforeſaid Word-bearer, was as a Son in his Minority, in his Father's Houſe. Then a Son little differs from the Servants, tho' he is the Heir; he is then under probation for the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. In his Pilgrimage on Earth, he was in a State of greater Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. At his Aſcenſion and Exaltation, he was then properly and moſt eminently aſſociated to the Empire of the Univerſe. This is properly God the Son, or the Man Chriſt Jeſus exalted, and in his Human Nature made the King of Kings under God; in which ſenſe, in the Scripture-ſtile, he may be ſaid to have created, or diſpoſed and modelled, all things in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, as <hi>Grotius</hi> ſhews, in his Annotations, on <hi>Col.</hi> 1, 16, and he may, as ſuch a Man, much more be ſaid to be God, than the Bread of the Euchariſt is ſaid to be his Body.</p>
               <p>Theſe things not only appear in a great meaſure conceivable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible, rational and free from intolerable difficulties, and in ſhort ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable and maintainable; but they ſeem perfectly agreeable to the Holy Scripture. The Primitive Antiquity, as I ſaid, ſeems very much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and uncertain about this moſt obſcure Subject, concerning which it was not impoſſible to miſtake, conſidering the great Generality and the myſterious and obſcure Manner in which it pleas'd the Holy Inſpiration of God to dictate it to the Sacred Writers, and conſidering the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy that than prevailed. (Howbeit, even by the Notions of <hi>Irenaeus, Juſtin Martyr, Origen,</hi> and all the Doctors that began ſo early in ſome meaſure to platonize, it ſeems that they were then proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Semi-Arians,</hi> and therefore rather <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> than otherwiſe: And, ſo, the Error of either ſide could not then be great.) But there is no Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and Authority like that of the Scripture. And it ſeems, that this kind of <hi>Arian</hi> or <hi>Semi-Arian</hi> Syſtem, which I have deſcribed in theſe two Letters, is the moſt agreeable to it.</p>
               <p>If I err in my Sentiment, I ſaid, I hope I am but of thoſe Weak in the Faith, who may be received, and whom God will receive; for I am heartily deſirous to know his Will, and the Truth, to follow it, and have fervently prayed him to ſhew it me, ſo far at leaſt as it is neceſſary to to be known. And this Unitarian Syſtem little differs from the Trinitarian.</p>
               <p>It ſeems indeed ſtrange, to addreſs diſtinct Prayers to the Divine Power. The Scripture doth it not. It ſeems in a manner as harſh, as to repreſent it as a diſtinct Deity; and it ſeems to do it, in making of it a Divine Perſon. And tho' the Man Chriſt Jeſus may be invocated, (by Wiſhes, when abſent, we find he is invocated in Scripture,) as Mediator between God and Man and as united to the Godhead; yet as a diſtinct ſupremely Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſon, is, I think, no where expreſly taught in Scripture, nor neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily deducible from any Argument. It ſeems Chriſt now is ſufficiently invocated here by us, when, both, we are denominated by him, and he is ſo call'd and relied upon in our Prayers, that our Petitions are put up to God in his Name, and that we therein offer up his Sacrifice to God, and plead his Merits and Interceſſion. This is actually to call upon his Name in Prayer,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106417:5"/>as is obſerved in <hi>the Brief Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> on <hi>Acts,</hi> 9, 14, and 21.</p>
               <p>As St. <hi>Jerom</hi> rejected and proteſted againſt the term, <hi>Perſons,</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> owned it to be improper, and Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> opined it ſufficed to ſay, <hi>Properties;</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> (Page 7th of his Book, which is intituled, <hi>The preſent State of the Socinian Controverſy</hi>) obſerves, that the Truth doth not depend upon the uſe of this, and other the like <hi>Scholaſtick</hi> terms; for, he owns, <hi>the true Faith was before them.</hi> Why ſhould they then be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed?</p>
               <p>By the ſecond and third <hi>Perſons,</hi> may thoſe partial Conſiderations of the Divine Mind be underſtood, the Divine Wiſdom, and Power or Inſpiration? There would then be no Difference in the Doctrine; for all do acknowledge theſe things to be in God. But for the Term, it cannot be warrantable, to impoſe the calling Wiſdom and Power, Perſons, for the reaſons aforeſaid. And, on the other hand, when God is worſhipped, can we then be wanting in our Worſhip of what is ſupremely adorable? That cannot be imagined.</p>
               <p>In ſumm. The term, <hi>Perſons,</hi> is not in Scripture, in ſpeaking of <hi>the Divine Nature.</hi> The Texts alledged for it, or for the ſenſe and import of that term, are very rationally ſuſceptible of another ſignification. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, the Divine Mind, Wiſdom, and Power, are owned to be in God, and to be God, or eternal, infinite, all-perfect; ('Tis granted, all that is in God is reducible to theſe three, Divine Intellect or Mind, Wiſdom, and Power; the Divine Will being implied in the Divine Power, or the Power in the Will, and the Divine Wiſdom comprehending the Divine Goodneſs and Juſtice) But then the Divine Mind is moſt properly the Divine Eſſence, and the Divine Wiſdom and Power are inconteſtably Divine Properties. ('Tis from <hi>Plato</hi>'s School, that Chriſtians learned to make <hi>Perſons</hi> of them.) And it ſeems manifeſtly, that the Doctrine of <hi>three Perſons</hi> in <hi>one God</hi> is encumbred with <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable Contradictions.</hi> What muſt I do? I cannot think otherwiſe of that term, nor of the <hi>Nicene</hi> and <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creeds, which uſe it, or imply it.</p>
               <p>I moſt humbly beſeech You, for God's ſake, to compaſſionate me, if I ſeem to miſtake in my thoughts concerning the ſcholaſtick terms. May theſe things be ſo conſidered and illuſtrated, that the Truth may be made to appear moſt conſpicuous, to all that are ſincere! I humbly beg your Prayers, and am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>P. S.</head>
               <p>If by <hi>the Word,</hi> and <hi>the Spirit</hi> ſhould ſeem to be underſtood <hi>ſome things, in the Divine Nature,</hi> ſomewhat <hi>analogous</hi> to <hi>Perſons;</hi> yet, <hi>firſt of all,</hi> it ſeems, at leaſt, they muſt be not only inferiour to the Father,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106417:6"/>but as it were ſome Portion (as <hi>Grotius</hi> notes, on <hi>John</hi> 1, 2,) or but ſome <hi>Beams,</hi> of his <hi>Perſon,</hi> (in ſome meaſure, as are to a Man his right Hand and left Hand,) inſomuch that the Father communicates of his Perfections to them but ſo far as he pleaſes. For the Scripture, as we have ſeen, (<hi>John</hi> 17, 3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8, 6, <hi>&amp;c</hi>) repreſents the Father not only as the Superiour, but as the whole Godhead; all that Chriſt and the Holy Spirit do, is aſcribed to the Father, as the Chief and Primary Cauſe, working in and by them; Chriſt ſays, that the Father who dwells in him doth the Works, that the Son can do nothing of himſelf, that the Son knew not when was to be the Day of Judgement, that the Spirit not only is ſent but is taught and commiſſionated what to do and ſay; and if the Practice of Scripture and the Texts to that purpoſe be exactly weighed, it ſeems that Chriſtians are not directed to addreſs their Prayers to the Son or the Spirit, but to the Father, or God in general terms. (For when in a Viſion Chriſt is both ſeen and heard ſpeak ſince his Exaltation, that is a particular caſe; there being no doubt, but that not only he is then to be perſonally honoured, but may then certainly be applied to, tho' not as a diſtinct and ſecond Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſon, yet as the Mediator between God and Men, and as the Viceroy of the Univerſe, aſſiſted by the Godhead, dwelling in him, as was ſaid.) It ſhould <hi>then</hi> be obſerved, Reaſon and Scripture plainly ſhew us, that the Divine Mind is endued with infinite Wiſdom and Power, as being the natural and neceſſary Perfections and Properties of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Mind it ſelf. But, that the Divine Wiſdom and Power are real and diſtinct Perſons, that particular Prayers ſhould be addreſs'd diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Divine Mind, diſtinctly to the Divine Wiſdom, and diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Divine Power, and that the Deity conſiſts of ſeveral real Things, or real Portions, whereof the one has excellencies above the other, ſeems unaccountable to the moſt ſedate Reaſon, and appears not expreſly ſpecified in the Word of God. Now it ſeems that from this conſideration, (all along enforced or made way for in theſe Two Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,) theſe two Inferences do neceſſarily follow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> We ſhould, then, ordinarily, and in common Aſſemblies, content our ſelves to direct our Prayers to the Father, or God in general terms, as the greateſt number of the reformed Churches do: (theſe, inconteſtably, would be the ſafeſt Meaſures, in ſo intricate a Matter; it being certain that when God is worſhipped, all is adored that is ſupremely adorable:) and we ſhould content our ſelves with the Apoſtles Creed, the Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions whereof are as general as thoſe of Scripture, whereas Human Terms, more deciſive, may be erroneous, and may cauſe juſt ſcruples in ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſe a ſubject.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> there is, then, truly no ſuch great Difference between the <hi>Trinitarians</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> but that the Terms of Church-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion may and ſhould thus be made ſo general as to comprehend them. For the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> will unanimouſly acknowledge, that there is in God
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106417:6"/>a Divine Mind endued with Wiſdom and Power; that the Wiſdom, whereby the World was contrived and redeemed, is communicated to our Saviour, from the beginning, as intimately as it is poſſible to be communicated, tho' he receives larger influences of it eſpecially ſince his Aſcenſion and Exaltation; (Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> in his laſt Book, intituled, <hi>The Proofe of our Saviour's Divinity explain'd,</hi> &amp;c. P. 211, owns this to be the whole meaning of what is call'd <hi>the Hypoſtatick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> or <hi>Incarnation</hi> of the Divinity with Chriſt's Human Nature;) that by this Divine Wiſdom God dwells in Chriſt, and is moſt intimately united with him; that Chriſt is to be honoured, as thus <hi>dignified;</hi> that the Godhead, which dwells in Chriſt, is to be ador'd with ſupream Worſhip; and that God has given to Chriſt the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Divine Power and Inſpiration, at his Deſire, without meaſure, or in the largeſt meaſure poſſible and neceſſary. (<hi>Grotius,</hi> on <hi>John,</hi> 3, 34.) Now, as was ſaid, it ſeems, this Divine Mind, Wiſdom, and Power, is all that the <hi>Trinitarians</hi> can mean by their term, three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. (The Scripture, as was obſerved, has not that term, <hi>three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in God:</hi> And it is certainly ſufficient to keep to the Scripture terms, eſpecially for a Means of Church Union.) On the other hand, the <hi>Trinitarians</hi> generally own, that one Divine Perſon, and eſpecially the Father, comprehends the Godhead; (as the Divine Mind cannot but be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as being joined with and inſeparable from the whole Divine Nature, as a Man's Head acting is the Man himſelf acting;) that therefore when God, or the Father, is worſhipped, the whole Godhead actually is thereby neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily worſhipped; that the Man Chriſt is not ſo God, as if the Manhood were changed into God, or ceaſed to be a Creature; that the Man Chriſt, being ſtill a Creature, tho one <hi>as much dignified as poſſible,</hi> is to be honoured, in the manner that the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> hold, as a Creature, <hi>as highly dignified as poſſible;</hi> and that Chriſt being to be honoured to the Glory of the Father, all the Honour to be paid him is to tend ultimately to God, even as the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> aſſert.</p>
               <p>It ſeems that if theſe Conſiderations were ſufficiently weighed, even the Agreement between the <hi>Trinitarians</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> would appear to be ſo great, as to juſtifie the Terms of Church-Communion pleaded for here, as in the <hi>Apologia pro Irenico Magno.</hi> But (I appeal to God to teſtify it) I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire above all things to be certainly informed, and directed in the Truth; and therefore if the Arguments and Reaſonings either here or in that Book are in any meaſure defective and erroneous, I do moſt heartily wiſh that it may be ſhewn in the Spirit of Chriſtianity. And if it may be ſhewn, the Subject doth well deſerve that pains, and it is to be hoped ſome Men may be found to be employed in that Work. But if the Notion of <hi>the Generality of Scripture,</hi> in this moſt intricate and abſtruſe Subject, be the true Standard of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> then, as was ſaid, Publick Prayers ſhou'd be directed to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or God in general terms, and we ſhould have no other Creed but that of the Apoſtles. The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian,</hi> even the <hi>Socinian,</hi> Syſtem ſeems ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Orthodox, and moſt Safe, as I have repreſented it, and there ſeems to be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106417:7"/>nothing deciſively expreſs in Scripture againſt it, but many things ſeem very much to conduce to confirm <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarianiſm.</hi> Moderation therefore ſeems here to be abſolutely neceſſary. And that's all, that is deſired. For then Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans would not judge one another any more, nor ſet ſtumbling-blocks in one another's way. And it ſeems, this Moderation cannot here be reaſonably denied. For (I cannot but repeat it) the leaſt that can be ſaid is, <hi>firſt,</hi> on the one hand, <hi>that</hi> this is a moſt difficult Matter, and the human Deciſions and uncertain and moſt probably unſcriptural Determinations in Publick Injunctions may be moſt unjuſt, dangerous and pernicious; and, <hi>ſecondly,</hi> on the other, <hi>that</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> honour the Man Jeſus Chriſt, and worſhip the Godhead dwelling in the Man Jeſus Chriſt, even as much as the <hi>Trinitarians</hi> can deſire, and no otherwiſe. But, by the Human Terms and Magiſterial Determinations, (which, both, aſſert three Divine Perſons, and make the Equality of the Son and Spirit with the Father to be an indiſpenſibly Neceſſary Point of Faith,) ſincere and pious Souls, for whom Chriſt died, may be driven out of the Communion of the Church, or deſtroy'd by Doubts and Fears and Scruples. The Proteſtant Principles, which imply that there is no living Magiſterial Judge of Controverſies and that all are to prove all things and judge for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſeem to require a greater Moderation and Generality in Terms of Church Communion, with reſpect to ſo very abſtruſe and intricate Matters.</p>
               <p>I find that a mighty ſtreſs is laid, on this conſideration, that in the ſecond and third Centuries, and almoſt ever ſince, the greateſt Number of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſeem to have been of a like Sentiment with the preſent <hi>Trinitarians.</hi> But it ſeems this Argument ſhould not be thought abſolutely infallible, for theſe reaſons, which the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> alledge, and which ſeem very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p n="2">I. Men, being apt to take wrong Meaſures, and often too preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, might ſoon deviate from the truth; as appear'd by experience, when the Generation next after <hi>Joſhua</hi> departed from the Law of <hi>Moſes, Judg.</hi> 2, 10, 11. All at once, ten of the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> irrecoverably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from the Inſtitution of God, 1 <hi>Kings,</hi> 12, 28, And at the ſame time, as at other divers times, all or the greateſt part of their Brethren did evil likewiſe in the ſight of the Lord, 1 <hi>Kings,</hi> 14, 22. So fickle then and weak are Men, that no ſtreſs is to be laid on their Practice; but our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe muſt be <hi>to the Law which is the Teſtimony,</hi> (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 8, 20.) Therefore the Unitarian Arguments, and eſpecially thoſe taken from Scripture, are ſtill at this day to carry it, if they be ſolid; for there is no Preſcription againſt the Truth.</p>
               <p n="2">II. A thouſand years in the ſight of God are as one Day, 2 <hi>Petr.</hi> 3, 8. And all Nations before him are as nothing, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40, 17. Yet a remnant ſhall be ſav'd, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9, 27. The little Flock need not fear, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12, 32. Tho reduced as low, as in <hi>Elias</hi> his Days, 1 <hi>Kings,</hi> 19, 10. The Gates of Hell, the Strength of Death and the Grave, or the Deſtruction of the Faithful, ſhall not finally ſo prevail, as wholly and for ever to extirpate the Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Truth off of the face of the Earth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16, 18. Therefore a time
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106417:7"/>may yet com, when the Earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the Sea, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11, 9.</p>
               <p n="3">III. It appears, that from the beginning there were great Numbers of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> that there have been <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> all along, and that many of them were the moſt learned of their time. Who, for inſtance, more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned than <hi>Theodotian, Symmachus, Paulus Samoſatenus, Lucianus,</hi> and <hi>Origen, Arius,</hi> and <hi>Euſebius,</hi> for theſe laſt as <hi>Arians</hi> or <hi>Semi-Arians</hi> may as well as the former be reck'ned <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians?</hi> Even from the 28th Chapter of the 5th Book of <hi>Euſebius</hi> his <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory</hi> it appears, that at leaſt a great Number of the Primitive Biſhops and Churches were <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians Juſtin Martyr</hi> owns <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> for his Chriſtian Brethren, <hi>Colloq. cum Tryphon. Jud. P.</hi> 207. But, by a Quotation in the aforeſaid Chapter of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> it appears the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> pretended they were all along in the firſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury the greateſt Number, and had the Succeſſion of Biſhops in their Sentiment in the moſt conſiderable Places even till Popes <hi>Victor</hi> and <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pherin,</hi> at the end of the ſecond Century; which doth not ſeem to be there diſproved, as it might then have been if it had not been true. <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> owns, the Jewiſh Chriſtians were generally <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians, Contr. Cels. L.</hi> 2. <hi>P.</hi> 56. It appears, that <hi>Theodoret</hi> doth the ſame, <hi>Haeret. Fab. L.</hi> 2. <hi>C.</hi> 3. For the Jewiſh Chriſtians eſpecially were call'd <hi>Nazarens</hi> as well as <hi>Ebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onites,</hi> as appears, <hi>Acts,</hi> 24, 5. <hi>Epiphan. Haeres. Naz. C.</hi> 1; <hi>Auguſtin. de Haeres. C.</hi> 9, 10.; St. <hi>Jerom. Epiſt. ad Auguſt.</hi> Thus it is own'd, the <hi>Ebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onites</hi> and <hi>Nazarens</hi> were no contemptible <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians;</hi> and they were thus nick-nam'd firſt by the unbelieving Jews, and in like manner probably by the Heathens, and afterwards by the platonizing Chriſtians. A few years after the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> the greateſt part of Chriſtians were <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians.</hi> In fine, there have always been ſome Unitarian Chriſtians in <hi>Aſia;</hi> and there are many Churches of them to this day, in the Dominions of the Pagan and Mahometan Princes, and even in <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> as well as in <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary, Solavonia,</hi> and <hi>Illyricum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. It is certain, that all the Doctors, that in the greateſt part of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Century were proſelyted from Heatheniſm, and that became the great ring-leaders, were wholly devoted to, not to ſay infatuated with, <hi>Plato</hi>'s Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy. Even the Popiſh Criticks complain of it, <hi>Huet. Origenian. L.</hi> 2. <hi>C.</hi> 2. And even ſome of them do inſinuate (what indeed cannot be doubted of) that upon that account the Writings of the Primitive <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> were deſtroy'd by the <hi>Trinitarians, Vales. in Euſeb. L.</hi> 5. <hi>C.</hi> 11. Now all the unſcriptural Terms, which are us'd concerning the Trinity and which have caus'd all the Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being found in the <hi>Platonick</hi> Philoſophers, and ſo many of the Primitive Chriſtians being avowedly <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> it cannot be queſtion'd or wonder'd from whence thoſe Terms were brought in, or which way came the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Doctrine.</p>
               <p n="5">V. It cannot be denied, but that about and ſince the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> the greateſt Violences have been conſtantly uſed, to ſuppreſs the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians.</hi> It is not ſtrange therefore, if they have been driven out of many Places,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106417:8"/>where the Governours perſiſted to perſecute them. Thus <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have been extirpated out of <hi>Spain, Bohemia,</hi> and in a great meaſure out of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. It ſeems inconteſtable, that the Primitive <hi>Trinitarians,</hi> or thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly held ſuch, differed from thoſe of the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> and their Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, and that theſe as well as the former differ from the preſent Schola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks. For the preſent Scholaſticks aſſert, that there is but one Divine Spirit, and that the Son and Holy Ghoſt are eternal and neceſſary Perſons, equal to the Father. The Nicene in their Creed ſay, that the Son is God of God, which implies diſtinct God of diſtinct God, or a diſtinct God, which title they give not to the Spirit. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> ſays, that many good Catholicks in his time would have been ſcandalized, if in the religious Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies the Holy Spirit had openly been ſaid to be God, <hi>Orat.</hi> 20. <hi>The Great</hi> St. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſays, that God is not one in Number, but only in Nature; (horrid Polytheiſm, perfect Heatheniſm, and too palpable a Demonſtration of the Miſchief of Platoniſm, and of the then prodigious Alteration of the true Doctrine!) and with the current of the Doctors of thoſe times he repreſents the three Perſons as being as diſtinct Beings as three Men, 141 <hi>Epiſt. ad Caeſariens. Irenaeus</hi> teaches, that the Father is greater than the Son, <hi>Adverſ. Haeres. L.</hi> 2. <hi>C,</hi> 49, and that beſides the Father and the Son no other is of his own Perſon Lord or God, <hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>C.</hi> 9. <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> who owns that he and at leaſt many Chriſtians in the ſecond Century ador'd and worſhipped the Prophetick Spirit and the Hoſt of the other good Angels together with God and his Son, (<hi>Apol.</hi> 2. <hi>P.</hi> 43,) affirms, that the Son had not a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Being, but was voluntarily begotten of the Father, that he is inferiour to him, miniſtring to the Will of the Father, (<hi>Ibid. P.</hi> 221.) that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begotten God, or the Father, doth not deſcend or aſcend from any place, neither is moved, ſeeing he cannot be contain'd in any place, but that this might be ſaid from the beginning of the World of the Son, who, ſais he, by the Father's Will is a God, and in the beginning before the Creation of the World was generated of the Father, <hi>Ibid. P.</hi> 221, and 280. Accordingly, <hi>Tertullian</hi> holds, that there was a time when the Son was not, <hi>Adverſ. Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen. C.</hi> 3. The Council which magiſterially condemned the Doctrine profeſſed by <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus</hi> and his Party, at <hi>Antioch,</hi> at the ſame time decred <hi>that the Son is not of the ſame Eſſence with the Father,</hi> as is even noted by <hi>Dalaeus,</hi> in his Treatiſe <hi>De uſu Patrum, Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. Thus by theſe very inſtances it appears, that the <hi>Trinitarians</hi> have ſo much varied, that a conſtant Tradition cannot be pleaded.</p>
               <p>For theſe ſeveral reaſons it ſeems, that too great a ſtreſs ſhould not be laid on the pretended (Eccleſiaſtical) <hi>Antiquity</hi> of this Sentiment, but, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that the chiefeſt Inquiry ſhould be, What appears moſt deciſive in <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> concerning the Points themſelves that are controverted, and concerning which it ſeems that the leaſt that can be granted is that with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to them we ſhould keep in <hi>Terms of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> to <hi>the Generality of the Terms of Scripture?</hi> If that ſhould prove a Miſtake, yet it is very fit that ſo important a Matter ſhould be moſt carefully conſider'd and debated, that the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106417:8"/>Errour may be evinc'd and confuted, by thoſe that may have the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to do it. But if this be no Errour, the not conſidering of it cannot but be moſt pernicious; wherefore I cannot but wiſh this were communicated to ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral learned Men, in order to their giving their Opinion and Reaſons concerning theſe things. It ſeems that (for any thing that appears to the contrary) by the Father, the Word, and the Spirit (in underſtanding them of God,) we may underſtand what the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> (then) underſtand thereby, Namely, God, and the Divine Wiſdom, and the Divine Power or Divine Inſpiration; and that our Prayers are to be addreſſed to the Father, or God in general terms. Moſt learned Men among <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> have been of that opinion. I have mentioned <hi>Calvin</hi>'s obſervation, that the acknowledgement of the Divine <hi>Properties</hi> is ſufficient, without inſiſting on the term, <hi>Perſons. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> ſays, it were better to call Almighty God, God, than Trinity. <hi>Poſtil. Major Domini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Forbeſius</hi> aſſerts, that the Perſons, as Perſons, are not the Object of Worſhip; that the adoring of them dictinctly, is extremely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious; that then divers Objects of Worſhip are repreſented; and that this Practice is founded on no Precept or Example of Holy Scripture, <hi>&amp;c. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Hiſtorico-Theologic. Part.</hi> 1. <hi>Qu.</hi> 31, <hi>a.</hi> 1. <hi>Caſaubon</hi> opines, that in ſuch accumulate repeated Invocations, the Church imitated the Heathens, who, not knowing which of the Gods or Godeſſes they had beſt apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to, therefore called upon them all, <hi>Exercit. P.</hi> 327. But we know, that the Spirit doth nothing but what he is commiſſionated, (<hi>John,</hi> 16, 13.) that the Father dwells in the Son, (<hi>John,</hi> 14, 10,) and that the Son doth nothing but what the Father ſhews him, (<hi>John,</hi> 5, 30.) Therefore incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtably it is ſufficient, to addreſs to the Father. And we ſhould content our ſelves to do ſo, for this reaſon, that it is ſufficient and ſafe, on the one hand, and, on the other, that the Unitarian Arguments appear very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, or, rather, unanſwerable.</p>
               <p>The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> ſhew; That all that Chriſt doth, he doth it by the Aſſiſtance of the Father; (<hi>John,</hi> 14, 10;) That, tho there is but one <hi>God</hi> properly, or in the moſt eminent ſenſe, yet that <hi>title,</hi> in <hi>Scripture,</hi> is ſometimes communicated to ſome <hi>Creatures,</hi> and is of the ſame import with that of <hi>Soveraign;</hi> (<hi>John,</hi> 10, 34, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) That Chriſt is not only the Word, or Great Meſſenger of God, but moſt eminently repreſents God, and is made, <hi>under God,</hi> the <hi>Soveraign</hi> of Men and Angels, and that God continually aſſiſts him in the diſcharge of his Office and continually doth for him at his requeſt all that is neceſſary to that end; (<hi>Hebr.</hi> 2, 8; <hi>John,</hi> 11, 42;) That (it being uſual among the Jews) it is the ſtile of the New Teſtament, to apply by way of <hi>accommodation</hi> ſome Sayings and Texts of the Old Teſtament, to ſome Events and Caſes or Circumſtances to which they may be applicable, in a ſenſe not exactly the ſame with that implied in the Ancient Prophets; (<hi>Matth.</hi> 2, 15. <hi>Matth.</hi> 2, 18. <hi>Matth.</hi> 2, 23. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3, 11, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10, 13;) That the New Creation, or New Model<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of all Things by the Goſpel, is by a Figure in the New Teſtament conſtantly compared to the firſt Creation; (<hi>John.</hi> 1.1. <hi>&amp;c) Mark</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106417:9"/>
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1, 10. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2, 5;) That, the Godhead moſt intimately dwelling and moſt extraordinarily operating in the Meſſiah, (ſo that the Man Jeſus Chriſt is the moſt glorious <hi>Schechina,</hi> figured by the Cloud in the Wilderneſs and by the Ark of the Jewiſh Covenant wherein God ſhewed himſelf preſent and before which the People of God worſhipped and proſtrated themſelves,) and Chriſt moſt eminently repreſenting God, being exalted to the <hi>Soveraignty</hi> of the Univerſe, and being aſſiſted with the Divine Wiſdom and Power, the New Teſtament, by way of accommodation, aſcribes to the Meſſiah, inveſted with that Power and Dignity, the moſt glorious Actions attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to God in the Old Teſtament, and the Divine Attributes and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties which may be ſuppos'd to be in ſome ſenſe or in ſome manner communicated to him by the Divine Indwelling; (<hi>John,</hi> 1, 1, <hi>&amp;c, Hebr.</hi> 1, 10. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18, 20. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28, 20. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1, 11. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2, 23.) That after all, in fine, the Scripture expreſly ſhews, that <hi>the Father</hi> is <hi>the only true God,</hi> or that the Father alone is God in the proper and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſenſe of that word, (<hi>John,</hi> 17, 3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8, 6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4, 6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24, 36. <hi>Mark,</hi> 13, 32. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) About two hundred Texts, diſtinguiſh God from Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Now, as Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> himſelf obſerves, in his Anſwer to the Biſhop of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> or <hi>The Scripture-Proofs of our Saviour's Divinity explain'd,</hi> &amp;c. P. 55, If but one Text of Scripture proves, that no other Perſon but the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alone is God, (as the five laſt quoted are in particular taken by the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians</hi> moſt expreſly to do,) that muſt put an end to this Controverſy, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe or juſtify all the Interpretations of Scripture given by the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> how harſh ſoever they may otherwiſe now appear. (The Dr. has that obſervation in ſeveral other places of that Book; Pages, 47, 50, 58.) It ſeems the Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Interpretations do not appear ſo harſh and unnatural, if the ſtile of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture be carefully attended unto, as may be ſeen in <hi>the Brief Hiſtory of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> or in <hi>Grotius</hi> his <hi>Annotations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For theſe reaſons, I conclude for <hi>the Generality of the Terms of Scripture;</hi> Scripture and Reaſon being the Light of God, (<hi>Pſ.</hi> 119, 105, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20, 27,) to which every one is to attend, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 10, 8, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10, 15,) no one being to judge for others in intricate Matters, but all being to unite in that which is Clear and Expreſs, or in the Latitude and Expreſſions of the Rule it ſelf, (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1, 24, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14, 13, and 19, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3, 16, &amp;c.) And if theſe reaſons are invalid to the concluding of the Fitneſs of ſuch a Method of Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, as I have mentioned, I earneſtly wiſh that their invalidity may be ſhewn, in the Spirit of the Goſpel. But if that Method be fit and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, then may it be followed, that God may be propitious to us, and that we may ſerve him as we ought to do, in Righteouſneſs, Charity, and true Piety! <hi>Amen!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. Line 13. for <hi>Deſiring or Willing</hi> read <hi>Willing or Deſiring.</hi> p. 2. l. 18. f. <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>this.</hi> p. 6. l. 1. after <hi>Scripture,</hi> add, <hi>which, like that of all the Eaſtern Tongues, is extraordinarily figurative.</hi> p. 8. l. 29. f. <hi>Iſ</hi> r. <hi>If.</hi> p. 8: l. 33. after <hi>Trinitarian,</hi> add, <hi>as the Modaliſts, who are the greateſt Number, do now repreſent it:</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106417:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
